Guide to the World War II Photograph Collection 1921-1963 (Bulk 1941-1945) PR 76
New-York Historical Society
World War II Photograph Collection
1921-1963 (Bulk 1941-1945)
New-York Historical Society
PR 76
2.7 Linear feet (7 boxes)
The World War II Photograph Collection includes promotional material from the United States War Department, the vast majority from the U.S. Navy.
Provenance
Gifts, 1941, 1942, 1943, 1945, 1946, 1947, 1950, 1957, 1959.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 30 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Scope and Content Note
The World War II Photograph Collection spans the period from 1941 to 1948 and includes promotional material from the United States War Department, the vast majority from the U.S. Navy. Photos are arranged alphabetically by creating agency and thereunder by subject. The collection includes approximately 2,000 black and white, 8 x 10" photographs and several smaller prints.
During processing, this material was removed from the Subject File. Members and equipment of the U. S. Navy, U.S. Army Air Force, and U. S. Coast Guard are shown. American pluck is a key feature of the photographs. Most photos have press information or narrative detail on the verso or on papers attached to the photo. The photos and their accompanying text give an idea of the breadth and message of the public relations campaign in America to encourage support for the war. Dates listed are the release date of the photos which, in the case of battles, was often several months after the event. In some instances groups of photos were released to commemorate important events. For example, a group of pictures showing the recovered ships sunk at Pearl Harbor was released in December 1942 for the one-year anniversary of the attack.
United States troops are seen in many different situations. Battle scenes mainly focus on bombing raids and burning ships in the Pacific arena. Italian POWS at a camp in New Jersey are shown. Both the German and Japanese surrenders are shown. Photos also include many U.S. ships involved in the war. The launching of battleships and aircraft carriers are well documented, as is the salvage of the cruise ship Normandie and its subsequent refitting as the U.S.S. Lafayette. Sailor life on board several ships, including the U.S.S. Missouri, is also shown. Some aerial views, once considered confidential, of ships in New York Harbor are contained in the U.S. Army Eastern Defense Command folders. Several New York area Naval Commandants are pictured, as well as many enlisted men at several different training facilities.
Women are displayed at work in many of these photos. Navy WAVES are shown readying themselves for battle as well as enjoying leisure activities. Photos of the New York Navy Yard in Brooklyn highlight women working as machinists and welders.
Throughout the collection, named subjects are filed first, and then miscellaneous photos are filed by date. In some cases, miscellaneous photos may complement the subjects in named series or folders; in these cases "see also" references have been given in the container listing.
Arrangement
Throughout the collection, named subjects are filed first, and then miscellaneous photos are filed by date. In some cases, miscellaneous photos may complement the subjects in named series or folders; in these cases "see also" references have been given in the container listing.
Missing Title
Series I: United States Army Photographs (1941-1945)
Series II: United States Coast Guard Photographs (1941-1945)
Series III: United States Navy Photographs (1921-1963)
Series IV: Other Photographs (1942-[1945])
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Other World War II-era material in the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections includes WWII Recruiting and Civilian Defense Posters in the Poster File (PR 55), prints in the Subject File (PR 68), and photographs in the John Albok Photograph Collection (PR 1) and the Radio Entertainers and Announcers Collection (PR 95).
Separated Material
Two published volumes were removed from the collection and cataloged in the New-York Historical Society library. These volumes are "Patchogue family album: Christmas greetings to our boys and girls in the Armed Forces, who by their gallant efforts won a victorious peace" and the program from the New York Retirement Federation of Civil Service Employees' 31st Entertainment and Reception (with a picture of the U.S.S. Missouri on the cover.)
Gelatin silver prints.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Area.; Snapshots; World War, 1939-1945 -- Concentration camps -- Germany.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- New Guinea.; World War, 1939-1945 -- New York (State) -- New York; World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda.; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Women.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Pictorial works.; ʻAbd al-Ilāh, Prince, 1913-1958; Aaron Ward (Destroyer: DD483); Buchenwald (Concentration camp); Chiang, May-ling Soong, 1897-2003; Civilian Defense Volunteer Organization; Dachau (Concentration camp); Franklin D. Roosevelt (Aircraft carrier); Missouri (Battleship: BB 63); New York Naval Shipyard; Normandie (Steamship); Plye, Ernie, 1900-1945; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; United States. Army Air Forces; United States. Army; United States. Coast Guard; United States. Navy
- Series I: United States Army Photographs
  Scope and Contents note
  A folder of Air Force "tear sheets" promotes the air forces' actions in Europe. U.S. Army Air Force pictures show men and women in training and combat. Photographs highlighting the Eastern Defense Command publicize how the Army defended the physical space of the United States: tracking ships, stationing anti aircraft guns. U.S. Army Signal Corps are shown at Watervliet Arsenal, in training camps, and as paratroopers.
  - Eastern Defense Command, 1942, 1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - U.S. Army Air Force -- Airmen and women, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-8)
  - U.S. Army Air Force - Combat, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - U.S. Army Air Force -- Planes, aloft, undated (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - U.S. Army Air Force - Planes, grounded, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - U. S. Army Air Force Tear Sheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - U.S. Army Signal Corps, 1941-1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - U.S. Army Signal Corps -- Editor's Day on Governor's Island, 1942 Apr. 18 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - U.S. Army Signal Corps -- Gen. Drum Inspecting Fort Hancock, 1943 Apr. 14 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - U.S. Army Signal Corps -- German Surrender, Rheims, France, 1945 May 5-7 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series II: United States Coast Guard Photographs
  Series II shows many New York-area locations of Coast Guard actions; the Hudson River, the Manhattan Beach USCG Station, a USCG Mooring Base on Travers Island in Pelham, NY, and the Statue of Liberty are all pictured. Photographs also highlight the Coast Guard Pharmacists Mates School at Columbia College of Pharmacy, the Coast Guard Hospital Corps, and the Coast Guard Training Academy in New London, CT. Implements such as lighthouses, ice cutters, and fireboats are common scenes in the photos. A photo of journalist Ernie Pyle is in Folder 19.
  - Manned Convoys, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - New York, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Queen Mary & Elizabeth, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ships, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Photos, 1941-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 22-25)
- Series III: United States Navy Photographs
  Folder titles are those used by the Navy Public Relations Department; folder titles in brackets were assigned by N-YHS Staff during processing. Often, the Navy-assigned titles sound ready for newspaper headlines. Some titles may seem to have no relationship to the photos to those unfamiliar with military terminology. "Baby Flat Top -- The Navy's Child Prodigy" is the title of a photo series showing life aboard an aircraft carrier. In "Shakedown," new recruits are taken on a practice mission in order to learn how to take care of a ship and to "get their sea legs."
  Most of the photographs highlight the Pacific theatre of war. Battles shown or highlighted (sometimes including the aftermath) include: the invasion of Borneo, Pearl Harbor, the Battle of Guadalcanal, the Makin Island Raid, the Battle of the Coral Sea, the Battle of the Solomon Islands, the Battle of Santa Cruz Island, and the Battle of the Philippine Sea. Navy troops are shown in Borneo, the Philippines (the subject of many photos taken throughout 1944 and 1945), Formosa, New Zealand, Guam, Saipan, New Guinea, the Marshall Islands, and the Solomon Islands. Other photographs show Navy Combat Troops landing at Attu in the Aleutian Islands.
  Photos showing the European front are mainly of Italy and North Africa, including "Operation Bootstrap" to liberate Italy. Photographs of Italy, including several titled "British fighting in Sicily" (folder 96), show "Naples in Ruins,"( folder 98) and troops landing in Anzio, Italy. Other European photographs include "U.S. Navy Crosses the Rhine" (folder 106), and others showing Le Havre, Brest, (folder 103), and beachheads throughout France (folder 102).
  Women are the subject of many photographs and photographic series. Women at work in the New York Navy Yard get much attention, as do the WAVES, the Navy's Auxiliary force for women. WAVES are seen in church, on deck of a ship (sunbathing, while sailors look on), "at chow," and in their summer uniforms. Folder 95 contains a photo of Madame Chiang Kai Chek reviewing WAVES at a New York training academy. Folder 102 shows Eleanor Roosevelt reviewing a group of WAVES.
  The New York Navy Yard (also known popularly as Brooklyn Navy Yard) is prominently featured in many photographs. The Navy Yard's activities peaked around October of 1944, with employment of over 70,000 workers working around the clock to build and repair ships for the United States Navy. The yard was made up of 6 dry docks, 2 building ways, 8 piers, 270 buildings, 19 miles of paved streets, and 30 miles of railroad tracks. Many ships launched from the Navy Yard are shown here, and several photo series show employees hard at work. One interesting photograph shows a visit by the Regent of Iraq to the New York Navy Yard (Folder 107.)
  Military technology and weaponry dominate the Naval photographs. Many photos of the U.S. Ships were taken up to 20 years after the end of the war. A large number of these photographs are not marked with the name of the ship. However, ships shown during wartime are well-documented and described on the verso of the photographs. Aircraft carriers are pictured in Folders 95, 98, 99, and 108. A model aircraft carrier is shown on display at Rockefeller Center in New York in Folder 107. "Helldivers," or bombing planes, are shown in folders 98. "Avengers," torpedo bombers, are shown in Folders 98, 101, and 105. "Hellcats," another bombing plane, appear in Folder 97.
  - [Aerial Views of New York Harbor], 1944 Nov. 7 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Allies Seize Green Islands, 1944 Mar. 13 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Baby Flat Top -- The Navy's Child Prodigy See also Folder 105, 1944 Apr. 30 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - Battle of Midway, 1942 Jun. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - [Commissioning Ceremonies and Launchings], undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - [Convoys], undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - [D-Day], 1944 Jun. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Fall of Ustica, 1943 Sep. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Floating Dry Docks -- "Field Hospitals" for Navy Ships See also Folder 107, 1945 Jun. 15 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Helldiver Flight Deck Crash Recorded Step by Step, 1945 Jun. 11 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Iwo Jima: Bloody Milestone on the Tokyo Road, 1945 Mar. 13 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Kiska Island Landing, 1943 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - [Motor Torpedo Boat], undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "Mulberry"--the Secret Floating Harbor, Normandy Landings, 1944 Oct. 23 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Naval Officer Training at Fort Schuyler, Bronx, New York, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - [Naval Training] See also Folders 92 and 105, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Naval Training Station, Samson, New York, 1942 Oct., undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Navy Advance Base Unit Hits the Beach at Lido, 1944 Sep. 19 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Navy Day in New York, 1945 Oct. 27 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Navy Testing New Uniforms for Enlisted Men, 1946 Jan. 4 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - New York Celebrates "Waves and Spars" Day, 1943 Feb. 8 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - New York Welcomes Nimitz, 1945 Oct. 9 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - [New York Navy Yard] See also Folders 91, 96, 101, 104, 106, 107, and 109, 1944, 1945, undated (Box 2, Folder 49-51)
  - New York Navy Yard Calls Women to Work, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - [Planes] See also Folders 99 and 101, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - [Plotting Ship Movements], undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Poster Designs, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - "Power in the Pacific" exhibit prints, [1945] (Box 3, Folder 56-57)
  - PT's Maneuver in Off-Shore Waters of an East Coast Port, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Shakedown, 1944 Jan. 31 (Box 3, Folder 59-60)
  - [Submarines] See also Folders 100 and 107, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Take Off for Tokyo, 1943 Apr. 20 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Torpedo Testing Range, Montauk Point, Long Island, 1944 Feb. 21 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - [U.S. Naval Reserve Midshipmen's School], undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - U.S. Navy Destroyer Escorts a United Nations Convoy, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - A U.S. Navy Transport Completes Mission, undated (Box 3, Folder 66-68)
  - U.S.S. Aaron Ward, 1945 Aug. 24 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - [U.S.S. Bon Homme Richard Launching] See also Folder 100, 1944 Apr. (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - [U.S.S. Enterprise], 1943 May (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - [U.S.S. Franklin D. Roosevelt Launching], 1945 Apr. 29 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - U.S.S. Iowa Launching, 1942 Aug. (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - [U.S.S. Kearsarge Launching], 1945 May (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - [U.S.S. Lafayette/Normandie Salvage], 1943, undated (Box 4, Folder 75-79)
  - A U.S.S. LST Joins a United Nations Convoy, undated (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - U.S.S. Missouri Launching See also Folder 107, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 81-84)
  - [U.S. Ships] See also Folders 93, 94, 98, 104, 108, and 109, 1921-1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 85-87)
  - [U.S. Ships], undated (Box 5, Folder 88-90)
  - Wake Island Attack, 1942 Feb. 24 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Navy WAVES at Floyd Bennett Field, New York, 1943 Jul. (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - [WAVES at U.S. Naval Hospital] See also Folders 94- 98, 100, and 102-104, 1945 Jul. 20 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Wartime Commandants, undated (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Miscellaneous Photos, 1941-1943 Oct. (Box 5, Folder 95-103)
  - Miscellaneous Photos, 1943 Nov.-1945 (Box 6, Folder 104-115)
  - Miscellaneous Photos, undated (Box 6, Folder 116-117)
- Series IV: Other Photographs
  Two folders of photos are from the Civilian Defence Volunteer Organization, and show war volunteers (often from the American Red Cross) relieving professionals for war duty and performing other important wartime tasks. Several folders of personal photographs are included in the collection. Sixteen snapshots of the Buchenwald and Dachau concentration camps were taken by a veteran who was present at the freeing of those camps in April 1945. Nine snapshots show Gerhardt Walter, the photographs' donor, in New Guinea in 1945. Eleven snapshots show New York City "dressed for war" with victory banners and flags hung from buildings and across streets, displays of unrationed food, and people in uniform.
  - Civilian Defense Volunteer Organization, undated (Box 7, Folder 118-119)
  - German Concentration Camps, [1945 Apr.] (Box 7, Folder 120)
  - Italian POW's, undated (Box 7, Folder 121)
  - Japanese Surrender, [1945] (Box 7, Folder 122)
  - Miscellaneous Photos, undated (Box 7, Folder 123-124)
  - Miscellaneous--Snapshots, 1942-1945, undated (Box 7, Folder 125-127)